Hello, today's דף daf is מ, mem, but we are on ל״ט
עמוד ב׳, lamed tet amud bet, so we've got to pick up
the pace. So at the top of ל״ט עמוד ב׳, lamed tet
amud bet, and the issue was here about dividing the sense of
the monetary of the of the monetary ownership of the slave, the
property ownership of the slave from the master-slave relationship.
And we said we had an interesting issue which is when a
גר, ger, a convert dies and he has no heirs to inherit
because, you know, if he was a natural-born Jew then every Jew
is as somehow part of the family, but if somebody converts, then
the biological family is not a family and if he has no
children, he has no heirs, so all of his property becomes ownerless.
So what happens to the slaves? So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
says, well, the slaves become free. They take possession of themselves, and
any personal status issues are irrelevant because there's nobody no master around
who's left to have to give them a שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur.
Whereas אבא שאול Abba Shaul says that that's true about the adult
slaves, but the minor slaves are not able to take possession of
property, so they remain free to be possessed by others. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemorah says bottom of ל״ט עמוד א׳, lamed tet amud
aleph, אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי הלכה כאבא שאול. Amar Rabi Yehoshua
ben Levi, Halacha k'Abba Shaul. אמר ליה רב זירא לרבי יעקב בר
אידי בפירוש שמיע לך או מכללא שמיע לך? Amar lei Rav Zeira
le-Rabi Yaakov bar Idi, be-ferush shemia lach o mi-klala shemia lach?
When you heard that teaching that we rule like אבא שאול Abba
Shaul from רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi, did you
hear him say it explicitly or was it inferred? אין מכללא. Inn,
mi-klala. So the גמרא Gemorah says מאי כללא? mai klala?
Where would we have inferred it from? So and you know, and
then maybe we can also question whether it would have been a
good inference. דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, D'amar Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi,
cause here's a teaching of רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabi Yehoshua ben
Levi in general. אמרו לפני רבי. Amru lifnei Rabi.
They said in front of רבי. Rabi. אמר נתייאשתי מפלוני עבדי. Amar,
nityashti mi-ploni avdi. If somebody says, I give up hope of ever
finding my slave, let's say he ran away, or let's say it's
just a way of saying I I I disclaim ownership over my
slave. So, another way of sort of being מפקיר mafkir the slave,
so you lose property ownership over him. Okay, then that's going to
still be the status about the question about what about his personal
status? Is that going to require a גט? get? מהו? ma hu?
What's the הלכה? halacha? אמר להם אומר אני אין לו תקנה אלא
בשטר. Amar lahem, omer ani, ein lo takana ela bi-shtar. He doesn't
have any way to fix his this situation except with a שטר,
shtar, a שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. So, meaning he still he A
is nobody can claim make lay claim to his labor, he owns
himself, he can go ahead and work for himself. On the other
hand, he himself cannot go ahead and marry a a Jew or
a non-Jew because he's in this middle situation, right? He's sort of
part he's not a slave, he's not a free man, his personal
status hasn't changed yet, he needs a שטר. shtar. Actually, that's a
debate of רש״י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafos. תוספות Tosafos says he's fully
a slave, he's fully a slave in terms of personal status. Again,
he owns his own labor, nobody can tell him what to do,
but his personal status is 100% slave and therefore he can continue
to be married to a non-Jewish woman. A not non-Jewish, to a
to a slave, a slave woman.
רש״י Rashi says he's in this in-between status and he can't be
married to either. Okay, but his status has not yet been resolved.
So that he still needs a שטר. shtar. Okay, so that's his
position, which is a position we've been seeing. Okay, ואמר רבי יוחנן
v'amar Rabi Yochanan and said רבי יוחנן, Rabi Yochanan, מאי טעמא דרבי?
mai ta'ama d'Rabi? What's the reasoning of רבי? Rabi? גמר לה לה
מאשה. Gamar lah lah m'isha. So it's very nice the גמרא Gemorah
sort of explores this idea, right? Because it's telling this idea that
it's still this personal status issue that's going on here even though
he's no longer owned. So just like a woman.
So there's a פסוק pasuk that says לאשה, l'isha, וכתב לה ספר
כריתות, v'chasav lah sefer krisus, the writing of the גט get to
make her to divorce her. And it says by a a female
slave, או חופשה לא ניתן לה, o chufsha lo nitan lah, her
freedom has not been given to her. So it connects the two,
the female slave and the woman in exactly a context of them
getting of them being like changing their personal status, gaining their freedom
if you want. So מה אשה בשטר עבד נמי בשטר. ma isha
bi-shtar, eved nami bi-shtar. So the same way a woman is her
personal status is changed through a document, through a גט, get, a
slave also, personal status needs to be changed through the giving of
a document. וקדייקת מינה, v'kadaikat minah, and you inferred from this, so
that is that's like the teaching of רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabi
Yehoshua ben Levi. Now what does that say about אבא שאול? Abba
Shaul? Okay, that's just saying that even after you don't own your
slave as property, you have to give him a שטר. shtar. What
does that tell you about אבא שאול? Abba Shaul? Because maybe here's
what you inferred from it. This is
מכללא. mi-klala. כי אשה, ki isha, just like a woman. מה אשה
איסור ולא ממון, ma isha, issur v'lo mamon, the same way a
woman only has the issue of personal status and not is not
owned as property. So אף עבד נמי איסור ולא ממון. af eved
nami, issur v'lo mamon. So a slave too, personal status and not
property. Meaning what? That the idea when the this גר ger dies,
right? He no longer owns them as property. Hold on let me
just check רש״י Rashi because I...
yeah it's a very strange inference because this is not talking about
the אבא שאול Abba Shaul scenario at all, but the way the
גמרא Gemorah is understanding it is the following: the same way this
idea is when the property is there's no longer... property, there's no
longer any property issue, there's just a personal status issue. That's the
whole scenario that he's talking about, that you need to give him
a גט, get, but he's no longer owned as property. And that's
exactly like a woman, right, who is not owned as property but
needs a גט, get, alright, so therefore, if you apply that to
the case of אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, in the case of אבא
שאול, Abba Shaul, right, you have a case where when the slaves
are adults and the גר ger dies, they're no longer owned as
property. And that's a case where they gain their own freedom. But
when they're not adults and they're minors, and therefore they don't own
the, you know, the property issue is still present, they don't gain
their own freedom. So I don't even really, if that doesn't make
any sense it's okay because I didn't understand it either, okay? I
really don't understand what the comparison here is to the אבא שאול
Abba Shaul case. And but somehow it's saying since this is a
teaching that is based on the idea that a שטר שחרור, shtar
shikhrur, at least in some situations when there is a master around,
exists in a status-only reality and not in a property reality, it
somehow that's going to tell us in the אבא שאול Abba Shaul
case that when you haven't yet addressed the property issues because they're
minors, you cannot somehow change their personal status. You first have to
address the property issues before you change their personal status, and since
you can't do that in a case by minors, you're stuck. Okay,
so that would have been the inference. So if that's the inference,
it's not a good inference. So the גמרא Gemara says ואם
מכללה מאי. Vi'im mikhlala mai. Okay, so ואם מכללה מאי, Vi'im mikhlala
mai, and the גמרא Gemara says, okay, let's say we did infer
it from that one. No, אמר ליה, Amar leh, so by the
way, that's an interesting pair of phrases in the גמרא, Gemara, right?
It's like, it's like מאי כללה Mai k'lala then and then you
know it's going to say ואם מכללה מאי. Vi'im mikhlala mai. Okay.
So when the גמרא Gemara says did you hear it explicitly or
did you infer it? Then they'd say wait a minute, where would
we have inferred it from? And it gives the story and it
gives the explanation. And then it says okay, and why does it
bother you that we inferred it from it? And now you know
it's like a setup to tell you because here's why it would
have been a bad inference. Okay. So ואם מכללה מאי, Vi'im mikhlala
mai, and if it was just inferred, and if it was just
inferred what's the big deal? So the גמרא Gemara says no, אמר
ליה אדרבה דוק מינה לאיפכא. Amar leh adarabba dok mina l'ipkha. No,
because I could have inferred the opposite. מה אשה בין גדולה בין
קטנה, Ma isha bein g'dola bein k'tana, you can divorce your wife
if she's an adult or a minor, אף עבד נמי בין גדול
בין קטן. Af eved nami bein gadol bein katan. So the case
about the slave in the אבא שאול Abba Shaul case could apply
that the status could change whether he's an adult or a minor.
Again, how we compare the case of, you know, we bring in
the אבא שאול Abba Shaul case which is completely different circumstances I
don't really get. But anyway, we'll just go with it. אמר ליה,
Amar leh, so he says no, בפירוש שמיע לי. B'feirush shmia li.
I heard it explicitly. Okay. So therefore you don't have to worry.
I heard explicitly that we rule like אבא שאול Abba Shaul in
this case of the גר ger who dies. ורבי חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן. V'Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan. Now רבי
חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba said in the name of
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, אין הלכה כאבא שאול. Ein halacha k'Abba Shaul.
We don't rule like אבא שאול. Abba Shaul. Okay. So that's a
different version of what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said. So אמר ליה
רבי זירא לרבי חייא בר אבא, Amar leh Rabbi Zeira l'Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba, בפירוש שמיע לך או מכללה שמיע לך? B'feirush shmia lakh
o mikhlala shmia lakh? When you heard about אבא שאול Abba Shaul
say, we rule, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say we don't rule like
אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, that the slave, the adult and the minor
slaves go free, did you hear him say that explicitly or did
you hear or did you infer? So the גמרא Gemara says, you
know what's coming up. So אמר
מאי כללה, Amar mai k'lala, where would you infer it from? דאמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי אמר לפני רבי נתייאשתי מפלוני עבדי מהו? D'amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi amar lifne Rabbi nisyashti miploni avdi mahu? The
exact same story. אמר להם אומר אני לא תקנה אלא בשטר. Amar
lahem omer ani lo takana ella b'shtar. You don't own him in
property, you still have to give him a שטר. shtar. ואמר רבי
יוחנן, V'amar Rabbi Yochanan, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan explains, מאי טעמא
דרבי? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi? Where is that coming from? גמר לה לה
מאשה. Gamar la la me'isha. מה אשה בשטר אף עבד נמי בשטר.
Ma isha b'shtar af eved nami b'shtar. So you see there's a
personal status issue that exists independent of the property. So this is
a thing that was taught by רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi and explained by רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So for the
first half of the גמרא, Gemara, we used it to infer רבי
יהושע בן לוי's Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi position. Here we're going to
use it to infer the exact opposite about רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan
position, because you could go either way with the גט get comparison.
You could say the גט get comparison teaches you it's relevant to
minors, because a גט get is relevant to minors, that's what we're
going to say next. Or you could say the whole idea that
there's only a property, the property issue has been dealt with, there's
only a personal status issue left, that's true by the adults who
take care of their property issue, but it's not true of the
minor slaves. Let's just get through this. So וכדדייקנא מיניה. V'k'd'daykana mineh.
ואמר רבי יוחנן מאי טעמא דרבי גמר לה לה מאשה. V'amar Rabbi
Yochanan mai ta'ama d'Rabbi gamar la la me'isha. Okay. וכדדייקנא מיניה, V'k'd'daykana
mineh, and you would infer from this comparison, כי אשה, ki isha,
just like a woman. מה אשה בין גדולה בין קטנה, Ma isha
bein g'dola bein k'tana, the same way you give a גט get
to a woman whether she's an adult or a minor, אף עבד
נמי בין גדול בין קטן. Af eved nami bein gadol bein katan.
This case of אבא שאול Abba Shaul could work whether it's an
adult or a minor. Again, comparing the case of giving a גט
get to a woman and אבא שאול Abba Shaul where they don't
need it because they free themselves, I don't exactly get. But anyway,
that would be the inference. Okay. That therefore it works whether it's
an adult or a
minor. ואם מכללה מאי? Vi'im mikhlala mai? So so what if we
inferred it from that? No, אדרבה דוק מינה להאי גיסא. Adarabba dok
mina l'hai gisa. You could have inferred the opposite. מה אשה איסור
ולא ממונא. Ma isha issur v'lo mamona. In the case by woman,
there's only a status issue, not a property issue. Okay. And that's
when you, that's what we're talking about. So אף עבד נמי Af
eved nami by the case of the slaves where the גר ger
dies, איסור ולא ממונא. issur v'lo mamona. they would only become free
once the property issue had been addressed when they took possession of
themselves, but they wouldn't become free in the case of the minors.
So אמר ליה, amar leih, so he said back, no, בפירוש, beferush,
I heard it explicitly. So I got to tell you, I did
my best, but I still don't understand it all how it's trying
to learn out from this case
about being מפקיר mapkir your slave from a property and then you
still need to give a שטר shtar because there's a status issue,
what that tells you about the question by אבא שאול Abba Shaul
when the slaves are left completely ownerless with the guy who died,
do they just automatically become free, right, or do they have to
take possession of themselves? It seems bottom line the question is in
that case where there is nobody to take possession of themselves. You
see we have I think been somewhat assuming and maybe this will
help frame it, we've been somewhat assuming it works through the monetary
issue. First you get rid of the monetary issue, you don't own
them as property, and maybe you can even do that independently, and
then you give them a שטר shtar and you free them in
terms of their personal status issue, right? And then the question is
and maybe that can come as a package, that can come separate,
first you do one, then you do the other. We see from
the case by the woman that you can change a personal status
even after there's without any property issue and so on. But maybe
it works the opposite way. This is a good question, right,
how does a standard שטר שחרור shtar shichrur work? Maybe a שטר
שחרור shtar shichrur works the opposite way. Maybe fundamentally what a שטר
שחרור shtar shichrur is doing is saying I'm changing your personal status,
I'm making you into a free man. And then the idea of
property ownership naturally falls away once you're fundamentally changing their personal status.
So it could be that that's the debate about the case by
the גר ger that dies. If it's somehow working
through the change of the property issue, so that doesn't work for
the minors because they can't take possession of themselves as property. But
if it's working about the change or through the change of personal
status and you say look, if there's no master around and nobody
owns them, just by definition they're free people, right? They don't have
to take possession of themselves if there's nobody who has that relationship
with them as master, then they are by definition free. And if
they're free, then they're their own property as well. So that works
by minors. They don't need to take possession of themselves because it
can start directly through the personal status aspect, right? So I think
that's like thinking about it by the case of the divorce by
the wife, right? She can take there can be the personal status
issue whether she's an adult or a minor. So anyway, although the
comparison is not precise, this גמרא Gemara does give us very nice
framings about what's going on here. By the case of גט, get,
the גט get only works as a personal status issue. By the
way, that's very nice in terms of the whole issue of קידושין
Kiddushin where we learn out that אשה נקנית isha nikneis is acquired,
and this גמרא Gemara underscores the idea that a woman is not
owned as property, it's only a personal status issue. So a גט
get is a personal status issue. And by a slave, right, how
can there's a status issue and a property issue? Can you divide
those? If you got rid of the property issue, does the personal
status issue go off automatically or does it remain, does it require
a גט get as well? That's the position of רבי. Rebbe. שמואל
Shmuel says it automatically falls away and then you also have the
similar application to the case by the עבדים, avadim, by the גר
ger who dies, where the minors slaves can't take property ownership of
themselves, but how much maybe do they become free just because their
personal status changed? Yes.
I was going to ask in regards to קידושין, Kiddushin, when you
say like for example the language of קונה את עצמו, koneh es
atzmo, so is that consistently a matter of status and איסור, issur,
correct?
That קונה את עצמו, koneh es atzmo, that's a status language?
Well no, that's part of the questions that come up in קידושין
Kiddushin whether it is meant as status or the simple meaning of
it is property. But the גמרא Gemara here underscores that a woman
is not property, right? We raised that at the very first דף
daf of the גמרא Gemara where the question is if the husband
isn't around, does בית דין Beis Din stand in for the husband
and claim that the גט get is a forgery because they have
to protect him because he's being like impacted by it? And the
רמב"ן Ramban says no, we don't protect the husband's interest. He's not
an interested party. The woman isn't his property. It's a question about
the woman's personal status. Yes. So when again and so when you're
using the language of ממונא mammona or property,
you're talking about like מעשי ידיה ma'aseh yadeha for example, like her
earnings? No, when the גמרא, Gemara, no, those that would say that
and I'm going to leave the rest of this conversation for קידושין,
Kiddushin, but those that would say that a woman is considered the
husband's
property and it's not just a status issue, it's not in terms
of her earnings, it's not
the same as a slave because a husband is only entitled to
his wife's labor rabbinically. It would be sexual property. That's the concept,
right, okay, that he has rights to her for sex, he owns
her as sexual property, or for her children.
In עבד eved it's מעשי ידיו. ma'aseh yadav.
Well, but no, a Jewish slave, עבד עברי, eved Ivri, is מעשי
ידיו, ma'aseh yadav, so the wife is Jewish, a free person, so
her also wouldn't be a full ownership. But a non-Jewish slave, an
עבד כנעני, eved Kna'ani, it's full ownership. You own him as he
is your property like your
car. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. I'm sorry, I'm just,
right,
so that's the thing, meaning that needs to be underscored that even
when הלכה Halakha constantly talks about them as property, it never loses
sight of the fact that they're also human beings, right? And therefore,
what's really, you know, shocking is, yeah, is that the תורה Torah
basically says that you could wind up being executed for if you
beat your slave and he dies, you know, within twenty-four hours and
so on. So that was like, you know, unheard of, like I
can't imagine anyone in the South of anybody who beat their slave
to death would be put in, would be tried and, you know,
whatever, they're your property, you could do with them what you want.
So the fact that, you know, the תורה Torah actually would, could,
you know, would do that is shocking, you know, for that type
of a context. So yes, the תורה Torah totally, you know, and
הלכה, Halakha, you know, completely at the same time treating them as
property recognizes them as human beings.
I don't know if that was de jure or de facto, you
know, might even have been de jure that they were, I don't
know.
Right, right, okay.
Right. Okay, could be he used a, some kind of monetary payment
instead of being killed?
No, he would actually be killed. Yeah, yeah. So although anyway, racial
slavery I think was of a different nature anyway than non-racial slavery.
Anyway, moving on.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, where are we? והתניא, Ve'ha tanya, you see, this is why
we don't get, we get behind because it's so interesting we have
to talk about it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay, now אמר מר, Amar Mar, אמר להם, Amar Lahem, so רבי
Rebbi says אומר אני אף הוא נותן דמי עצמו ויוצא ולא קנה
אלא בשטר. Omer ani af hu notayn d'may atzmo ve'yotzei ve'lo kani
ela be'shtar. So we're going to move away from the אבא שאול
Abba Shaul case, the comparison was a little strange, to get to
this basic statement that we've been dealing with, this fascinating case of
he's no longer his property and רבי Rebbi says he still needs
a שטר Shtar to change his status. והתניא, Ve'ha tanya, but we
taught in a ברייתא, Braitah, רבי אומר אומר אני אף הוא נותן
דמי עצמו ויוצא מפני שהוא כמוכרו לו. Rebbi omer omer ani af
hu notayn d'may atzmo ve'yotzei mipnei she'hu kemochro lo. We remember that's
the case before when a guy was מקדיש makdish his slave to
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and רבי Rebbi says the, he can
pay for himself, the slave can buy himself from the גזברים gizbarim
and then he would go free. So what happened to the שטר
shtar there? Okay, why did that work? I thought you said he
needs a שטר shtar so the owner doesn't own him anymore, but
what about the שטר? shtar? So the גמרא Gemara says הכי קאמר
או בכסף או בשטר. hachi ka'amar o be'kessef o be'shtar. No, no,
one of the ways that a slave is freed is through כסף.
kessef. It's interesting, we've only been focusing on שטר shtar because we've
been talking about you just renouncing your property ownership over it. Okay,
but you know the גמרא's Gemara going to learn like from the
פסוק או הפדה
לא נפדתה o hu hafdeih lo nifdasa by a שפחה כנענית, shifcha
kna'anis, right, she has not been redeemed. But if somebody actually buys
his freedom, I pay the master for the freedom of the slave
or the slave himself pays the master, the act of giving כסף
kessef is a formal act that actually frees. So you need a
formal ritual, I'll call it a ritual, but anyway some type of
a formal act, okay, to do the act of freeing. It's not
enough that he happens to be not owned by anyone. So if
I just מפקיר mafkir him, there was no act of redeeming, so
he still needs a שטר. shtar. But if he actually buys his
freedom from me, that's an act of redeeming and then he goes
free without a שטר. shtar. That is an act also that changes
his status. By the way, that question about how does a slave
become free, is it through the renouncing of ownership or through addressing
his personal status, that could depend whether you do it by שטר
shtar or by כסף. kessef. If you do a שטר, shtar, it
focuses on changing his status and the property thing falls away automatically.
If he redeems himself, you focus on the act of, you know,
of relieving him as property and then the status follows. But it
still would be different than מפקיר mafkir because still there needs to
be a formal defined act that does it, not just the reality
that he is no longer owned.
And an עבד כנעני eved kna'ani has monetary holdings?
He can, I mean if you can give a slave money that
is on the condition his master doesn't own it. Normally redeeming would
come through a third party, but that could be. Actually in ancient
Rome, you know, some slaves were like, you know, were very wealthy,
they were slaves that owned slaves. All right,
anyway, it was very different like than the South. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, אלא בשטר והתניא. ela be'shtar ve'ha tanya. הכי קאמר או בכסף
או בשטר. hachi ka'amar o be'kessef o be'shtar. So the גמרא Gemara
says והאי פקע ליה כספי, ve'hai paka lei caspei,
but in רבי's Rebbi case there you could no longer do the
act of redeeming because there was no longer any monetary ownership. Remember
the case was I was מפקיר mafkir my slave and the only
thing left to do is now give him a שטר, shtar, okay,
because we've now made it not possible to do the act of
redeeming because there's no longer any property ownership left. Okay, a normal
slave that's owned, you have two paths to make him free, שטר
shtar or כסף. kessef. But a slave that I מפקיר, mafkir, that
was not an act of redeeming, and the only path left, because
redeeming doesn't make sense if I don't own him as property, the
only act left is the act of giving a שטר. shtar. והאי
פקע ליה כספי ולאפוקי מהאי תנא, ve'hai paka lei caspei u'lafokei mei'hai
tanna, to exclude the position of this other תנא, tanna, דתניא, detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא, Braitah, רבי שמעון אומר משום רבי עקיבא.
Rebbi Shimon omer mishum Rebbi Akiva. יכול יהיה כסף גומר בה כדרך
ששטר גומר בה? yachol yi'hiyeh kesef gomer bah k'derech she-shtar gomer bah?
So here's a statement that כסף kesef does not work to free
a slave. The question is, maybe כסף kesef should work the same
way a שטר shtar works to free a slave, and the גמרא
Gemara says, תלמוד לומר והפדה לא נפדתה. Talmud lomar v'hipadeh lo nifdata.
This is the story about the what do you call it?
about the שפחה כנענית, shifcha Kena'anit, that she has not been redeemed,
okay, and then it says או חפשה לא ניתן לה, o chufsha
lo nitan lah, or her freedom has not been given to her.
So the דרשה drasha is גורא כל הפרשה כולה לחופשה, gora kol
haparasha kulla l'chufsha,
okay, the whole thing is sort of, you know, is reduced to
the end of the פסוק pasuk that says she has not been
freed, so although it talks about her being redeemed, it ends by
חופשה לא ניתן לה, chufsha lo nitan lah, her freedom hasn't been
given to her, and therefore he's reading the פסוק pasuk not to
say these are two paths, redeeming or some act of manumission, no,
even if it's redeemed, ultimately it requires a חופשה, chufsha, it requires
a שטר shtar to change her status. Okay, לומר לך שטר גומר
בה ואין הכסף גומר בה, lomar lacha shtar gomer bah v'ein hakesef
gomer bah, the only thing that changes a slave's status is a
שטר shtar and not כסף. kesef. So, very interesting question about how
does a slave, what's the act of freeing a slave? And again,
the question might be seen, כסף kesef might be talking about, it's
possible to work if you do the right formal act through the
property dimension as well. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אמר רמי בר חמא אמר רב נחמן הלכה כרבי שמעון, Amar Rami
bar Chama amar Rav Nachman halacha k'Rabbi Shimon, we rule like רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, and I'm trying to remember even which רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon it was, it's been so long. What's the רבי שמעון?
Rabbi Shimon?
Oh my god, I forgot. What's the רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon?
Somebody help me!
Where's רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon?
None of your Englishes are reminding me where the רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon is. I'm sorry, I prepared this. Oh, it's right here! No,
no, no, wait a minute.
I prepared this two days ago, that's the problem about being behind.
Is it right here? Am I missing a רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
right here?
There's one about the hair being cut, do you want that?
Is that it?
There's a thirty-nine and a thirty-nine
a... ונתנה
תנא
קמא ורבי שמעון... u-netana tana kamma v'Rabbi Shimon...
Oh wait, is this the point right here? One minute. Oh, I'm
being so stupid. It's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the name of
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. You see that? I focused on רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, like when
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is in the room, I lose sight of
everybody else. Anyway, I apologize. Okay, it was what we call רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. I know, I know. Anyway, but it's claiming this
as רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, even though it was he's saying in
the name of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. I'm sorry. Okay, so do
we rule like this? So that's exactly our question, sorry, is do
you say that a slave can be freed through כסף kesef or
or only through שטר shtar or even through כסף? kesef? So רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, what we're calling רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, says only
by שטר. shtar. Okay, so let's take a look. So אמר רמי
בר חמא אמר רב נחמן הלכה כרבי שמעון, Amar Rami bar Chama
amar Rav Nachman halacha k'Rabbi Shimon, we rule like רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, it's only by שטר, shtar, not by כסף. kesef. רבי יוסף
בר חמא אמר רבי יוחנן אין הלכה כרבי שמעון, Rabbi Yosef bar
Chama amar Rabbi Yochanan ein halacha k'Rabbi Shimon, no, it can also
be by כסף. kesef. אשכחיה רב נחמן בר יצחק לרבא בר שילת
דהוה קאי אפיתחא דבי תפילה, ashchechi Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak l'Rabba bar
Shila d'hava kai a-pitcha d'vei tfila, so he was standing, so he
saw him standing by the door of of a house of prayer,
at present called a בית תפילה, beit tfila, as opposed to בית
הכנסת. beit haknesset. Anyway, אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him,
הלכה או אין הלכה, halacha o ein halacha, do we rule like
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon or not? אמר ליה אני אומר אין הלכה,
amar lei ani omer ein halacha, I say we don't rule like
him, that כסף kesef also works. ורבנן דאתו ממחוזא, v'rabbanan d'atu mi-Mechuza,
but the rabbis who are visiting from מחוזא, Mechuza, אמרי אמר רבי
זירא, amri amar Rabbi Zeira, they say in the name of רבי
זירא Rabbi Zeira משמיה דרב נחמן הלכה, mishmeih d'Rav Nachman halacha, from
the name of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, הלכה, halacha, that we rule
like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that it's only שטר shtar not כסף.
kesef. ורבנן דאתו ממחוזא אמרי, v'rabbanan d'atu mi-Mechuza amri, but the rabbis
who are visiting from מחוזא Mechuza say, אמר רבי זירא, amar Rabbi
Zeira, they say in the name of רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira משמיה
דרב נחמן, mishmeih d'Rav Nachman, no, I did skip a line? No,
okay, הלכה, halacha, yeah, I said I said it, we do rule
like it, we do rule like it, כסף kesef does not work,
we rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon only שטר. shtar. דכי אתאי
לסורא, d'ki atai l'Sura, then when I came to סורא, Sura, אשכחתיה
לרבי חייא בר אבין, ashchateih l'Rabbi Chiyya bar Avin, I found רבי
חייא בר אבין. Rabbi Chiyya bar Avin. אמר לי אימי לי איזה
גופו של עובדא היכי הוה, amar li eimi li eizeh gufo shel
uvda heichi hava,
tell me the exact events, what occurred that you came to this
conclusion about that we rule that it's only שטר shtar and not
כסף. kesef. So אמר לי, amar li, he said to me, that
that was the conclusion you came to, that we rule like רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon and it's only שטר shtar and not כסף. kesef.
So אמר לי, amar li, he
said to me, דההיא אמתא, d'hahi amta,
there was a maid a slave woman, דהוה מרה שכיב מרע, d'hava
marrah shechiv mera, her master was on his deathbed, אתיא בכיה קמיה,
atya bachya kameih, she came and cried in front of him, אמרה
ליה עד אימת משתעבדנא ותיזיל לההיא איתתא, amra lei ad eimat mishta'avadna
v'teizil l'hahi itata,
how long will I be enslaved, I've been your slave for seventy
years, you're about to die, like how long do you expect me
to be your slave for? So basically can you like free me
on your deathbed here at least? So שקל קומסתיה, shakal kumsei, he
took his like hat, שדא בה, shada bah, he threw it at
her, ואמר לה זילי קני הא וקני נפשך, v'amar lah zili kni
ha u-kni nafshach, and he said to her, go take this hat,
take this hat, and acquire your own freedom. Okay, so it's very
nice, but what type of act of freeing a slave's that? Okay,
אתו לקמיה דרב נחמן, atu l'kameih d'Rav Nachman, they came to רב
נחמן, Rav Nachman, אמר להו לא עשה ולא כלום. amar lehu lo
asa v'lo klum. He didn’t do anything, he didn’t free her. He’s
got a feel for this slave woman anyway. So poignant! Anyway, so
from there we inferred that רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* said that כסף
kesef. *Kesef* doesn’t work to free a slave. There’s a little bit
of a problem though. That doesn’t show you that כסף kesef *Kesef*
doesn’t work to
free a slave. When we say כסף *Kesef* works, who’s giving the
money to who? It’s the slave who’s giving it to the master.
So מאן דחזי סבר משום דלא כרבי שמעון *Maan dechaza savar mishum
dela k’Rabbi Shimon*. We’re like רבי Rabbi. שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* that כסף
*Kesef* doesn’t work. ולאו היא *V’lav hi*, if that’s not the reason,
אלא משום דהוה ליה כלי של מקנה *ela mishum dehava lei keli
shel makneh*, because it’s the one that is like if you think
about a קנין חליפין *kinyan chalipin* example, it’s interesting how the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is shifting to חליפין *chalipin* language, but in a חליפין
*chalipin* language, I, I’m the קונה *koneh*, I’m trying to buy your
field, I give you the handkerchief and I get your field. It’s
sort of like a quasi כסף *Kesef*. Okay, but that’s called כלי
של קונה *keli shel koneh*. If you give me the handkerchief and
you’re selling me the field, that doesn’t work. So it’s the same
thing here, right? It has to be an exchange. The one who’s
getting the free, the other side gives the money to the master.
And here it was the master who was giving the money to
the woman and therefore it’s not going to work. Okay. All right,
so we still don’t know whether כסף *Kesef* works as a way
of freeing a slave.
It seems like it should work though because he’s, I mean, he’s
giving her something
that’s of value to her.
Yeah, so where do we see though?
He may not be receiving anything, right? Right.
But
if we conceptualize that there’s two things: a שטר shtar, *shtar*, like
a גט get *get*, that focuses on status, or an act of
redeeming the slave. How is him giving her money an act of
redeeming the slave?
If we say I can be קונה *koneh* your field when I
give you כסף *kesef*, does that mean that when you give me
כסף *kesef* I can be קונה *koneh* your field? In his field,
I know.
Okay.
How does it work when a woman is through the rabbis, when
a woman directly is מקנה *makneh* the חובות *chovot* of the כתובה
*ketubah* to the, to the husband and vice versa? Why is she
מקנה *makneh*?
No, no, no, she’s not מקנה *makneh*, he, the, in the כתובה
*ketubah* the husband takes the handkerchief and the husband obligates himself to
the woman, the rabbi stands in for the woman there.
Right, so but the woman is
being, the woman is מקנה *makneh*. No, she’s not obligating herself, the
כתובה *ketubah* spells out the husband’s obligation.
But that’s because it’s about obligation, not about a redemption, not about
redeeming something.
Well,
either way, the side that, it’s an exchange. You have to think
about these things as an exchange. So if you’re the one taking
the handkerchief or you’re the one taking the money, it means that
you’re the one giving something in exchange. So you’re giving your, your
financial obligations, you’re giving the slave her freedom, you’re giving something back.
Right. So okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אלא
רב שמואל Shmuel בר אחיספיי אמר רב *ela Rav Shmuel bar Achisfei
amar Rav*, הכי אמר רב המנונא סבא *hachi amar Rav Hamnuna Saba*,
אמר רב יצחק בר אשין אמר רב הונא אמר רב המנונא *amar
Rav Yitzchak bar Ashin amar Rav Huna amar Rav Hamnuna*. Wow, that’s
a long tradition. הלכה halacha כרבי שמעון *Halacha k’Rabbi Shimon*. We rule
like רבי Rebbe, שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, long tradition that it’s only שטר
shtar *shtar*, not כסף *kesef*. ולאו היא *V’lav hi*, אין הלכה halacha
כרבי שמעון *ein halacha k’Rabbi Shimon*. Okay, so that’s the last word
that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has on that. All right. אמר רבי
זירא Rabbi Zeira, אמר רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina, אמר רב אסי אמר
רב *Amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rabbi Chanina amar Rav Assi amar Rav*.
Now another tradition. עבד שנשא בת חורין בפני רבו bifnei rabo. *Eved
shenasa bat
chorin bifnei rabo*,
now it’s actually going to be actually a little different and a
little fun, I didn’t think this was fun. Anyway, if a slave
marries a free woman in the presence of his master, they do
a whole חופה chuppah *chuppah* or whatever and the master doesn’t say
anything, יצא לחירות yatza lecheirus. *yatza l’cherut*, he goes free. Now what’s
happening here? Although it uses the phrase יצא לחירות *yatza l’cherut*, everybody
says, I don’t know if there’s somebody who reads the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* differently, but pretty much the whole consensus is that obviously this
is not an act of freeing a slave. Where’s the שטר shtar
*shtar*? Where’s the כסף *kesef*? What it means is it’s evidence that
the slave has already been freed, and we take that as evidence.
The master would never allow his slave to marry a free woman,
right, if the slave was still a slave. So he wouldn't, so
therefore the fact that he’s doing it and not saying, it’s being
done in front of him, he’s not saying anything shows that he’s
already freed his slave.
That’s a רש''י Rashi *Rashi*.
Right, that’s a רש''י Rashi *Rashi*. אמר ליה amar lei: רבי יוחנן
Rabi Yochanan, כגון זה בידך *Amar lei Rabbi Yochanan kegon zeh b’yadecha*,
you have this teaching in your hand? ואני שונה *v’ani shoneh*, and
I have a teaching that challenges it. הכותב שטר אירוסין shtar eirusin
לשפחתו *Hakotev shtar eirusin l’shifchato*, if somebody writes a document to his,
to his female slave that he’s marrying his female slave, הרי את
מקודשת לי Harei at mekudeshet li, *harei at mekudeshet li*, and he,
he’s trying to marry his female slave. Okay, why, you can’t do
that, right? She’s not a free woman. So, and so maybe that
should be proof that you’ve actually freed her. So, and nevertheless it’s
a debate, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir אומר מקודשת mekudeshet וחכמים אומרים אינה
מקודשת *Rabbi Meir omer mekudeshet v’chachamim omrim einah mekudeshet*. It’s a debate
between רבי Rebbe, מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and חכמים *Chachamim* whether it works.
Okay, but couldn’t you, we said she should definitely be מקודשת *mekudeshet*,
it should be proof that he’s already freed her. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*
says, no, כי אמר רב אבא בר רב הונא שילא *ki amar
Rav Abba bar Rav Huna Shila*, כששיחררו הניח לו תפילין tefillin *keshe’shichrero
hiniach lo tefillin*. No, no, no, we’re going to talk later about
a slave putting on תפילין tefillin *tefillin* and ask, does that really
prove anything? And we say no, it proves it if the master’s
directly involved. If he’s putting תפילין tefillin *tefillin* on the slave, he’s
wrapping it around the slave’s arm, that shows, because slaves wouldn’t wear
תפילין tefillin *tefillin*. shown that shows that he must have freed him,
okay? But the so when we talk about things demonstrating that you
must have
freed your slave, it's when you're actively involved in the process. So
the same way we're going to say that here, we'll say that
we'll reinterpret our case about the slave getting married and the master
being present. So, הכא נמי hacha nami, כשרבו השיאו אשה. We're talking
not that just the slave married a woman, but the master was
directly involved, he made the שדוך, shidduch, he arranged for the חופה
and so on. So fine, that limits that case of when we
assume he's freed, but it doesn't deal with the problem about when
the master is directly trying to marry his female slave, he's directly
involved there, why doesn't that prove that he's freed her? Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this, one minute. ומי איכא מידי דלעבדיה
לא עביד ליה איסורא? Umi ika midei delevdei lo avid lei issura?
So when we say if he married his slave to a free
woman, then it shows he freed her because he never would have
his slave, you know, be involved in this transgression of a slave
and a free woman. וליה עביד איסורא? Veleih avid issura? But same
thing, when he is trying to marry a slave, why don't we
also say he wouldn't do a transgression himself? Let's use it as
evidence that the slave woman is free. But you haven't answered the
question, why when he himself was trying to marry this slave woman
isn't it evidence that he freed her? So the גמרא Gemara says
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak הכא במאי
עסקינן, Hacha bmai askinan, here what are we talking about? דאמר לה
צאי בו והתקדשי בו. deamar la tzei bo vehitkadshi bo. It's clear
in the context of how he's trying to marry this slave woman
that he is still that he has not yet freed her. What
he says to her is, here is your שטר קידושין, shtar kiddushin,
okay, and with this שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin you should also, this
should also serve as a שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. You guys with
me? So he's saying, it's clear, if he just said, took a
ring and said to a slave woman, הרי את מקודשת לי בטבעת
זו, Harei at mekudeshet li betabaat zu, we'd say, oh, he must
have freed her before, he never would have done that, and we'll
take that as evidence that he freed her. But if he goes
ahead and writes a שטר, shtar הרי את מקודשת לי, Harei at
mekudeshet li, and when he gives her the שטר shtar he says,
through this שטר shtar. I, you will be married to me and
you will be freed. I'm going to make this as also a
שטר shtar. אירוסין and a שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. Can it count
as both? Okay. Now you would think it would have to have
the, well, whatever, they come at the same time, but you would
think it has to have the language. How could הרי את מקודשת
לי, Harei at mekudeshet li where's the language of שחרור? shichrur? He
might want it to function as such, but it's not written as
such. So that's going to be the debate. Okay. רבי מאיר סבר
יש בלשון הזה לשון שחרור. Rabbi Meir savar yesh belashon hazeh lashon
shichrur. הרי את מקודשת לי Harei at mekudeshet li implies that you're
being freed now. And why does it imply you're being freed? You
could say it two ways. Number one, the גמרא Gemara’s before, עם
קדוש קאמר, Am kadosh kaamar, so מקודשת might have, you know, that
suggestion of that idea. But more to the point, because it's implicit.
You can't be married to me unless you're free, and since I'm
saying that you're going to be married to me, so it's like
the document is saying that I'm freeing you. But it only works
because it's a document, it's a שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. If I
gave the ring and said הרי את מקודשת לי Harei at mekudeshet
li, and את משוחררת at meshuchreret at the same time, it wouldn't
work because it's not שטר shtar, and it's not כסף. The כסף
is going in the wrong direction. But because it's written הרי את
מקודשת Harei at mekudeshet, לי, and רבי מאיר says that suggests that
she's freed, it would only be possible if she's freed, it's like
the שטר shtar. is saying I am freeing you. One minute. ורבנן
סברי אין בלשון הזה לשון שחרור. Verabbanan savri ein belashon hazeh lashon
shichrur. No, that's not, it's not explicit enough. So that's like a
long fascinating debate, right? Does that count as a שטר שחרור shtar
shichrur at the same time? But that's not relevant for our issue.
In that case, it was clear by the context that she was
still a slave. We're talking about using something as evidence about what
happened in the past. And we're saying because the master's directly involved
in doing something that's prohibited for a slave to do, or that
a slave normally wouldn't do, by society it would be an, you
know, non-acceptable
for a slave to do, like the תפילין tefillin case which we're
going to get to, and he's directly involved, that will serve as
evidence that he did
free the slave in the past. Yes, Charlie. That first thing, רבי
זירא, רבי חנינא, רב אשי, Rav Ashi, רבי.
Yes, רב אשי Rav Ashi doesn't belong there, he's much later than
the rest of them. I don't know what to tell you about
that.
There maybe they are two רב אשיs, Rav Ashi I don't know
what to say. Okay, yes. I just want to point out that
the entire conceptual framework from the earlier סוגיא sugya of מכלל דבכללא
michlal devechlala is now in... ah, that's a nice point. Right, the
whole thing about... both cases. Oh, that's brilliant. You mean both in
terms of... oh, that's really nice. You mean both in terms of
the language of הרי את מקודשת, it's like מכלל michlal that I'm
freeing you, and the acts of marrying the slave, putting תפילין tefillin.
on the slave is a case about מכלל, michlal, can we infer
about what some... oh, that's really... that is very, very nice. אשריך.
Ashreicha. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, אמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי. Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. Now we get
to the thing about the תפילין tefillin that we referred to before.
עבד שהניח תפילין בפני רבו, Eved shehiniach tefillin bifnei rabo, יצא לחירות.
If a master puts on תפילין tefillin first we start with in
the presence of the master, he goes free. מיתיבי, Meitivei, because we
assume that he's been freed. לוה הימנו רבו, Lava heimenu rabo,
if the master borrowed money from his slave. או שעשאו רבו אפוטרופוס,
O sheasao rabo apotropos, or maybe he made him a like a...
with a guardian sort of like a יוסף Yosef situation. או שהניח
תפילין בפני רבו, o sheniyach tefillin bifnei rabo, or he put on
תפילין tefillin in the presence of his master, או שקרא שלשה פסוקים
בבית הכנסת בפני רבו, o shekara shlosha pesukim beveis hakneses bifnei rabo,
he got an עליה aliyah in שול, shul, that’s what it means,
right? Called, get called up and get an עליה. aliyah. Okay, all
those are things that either by more by society than by הלכה
halacha. would not happen with a slave, and nevertheless the ברייתא braisa
teaches הרי זה לא יצא לחירות. harei ze lo yatza l'cheirus. It’s
not sufficient evidence. And one of those things is תפילין. tefillin So
how could you say that תפילין tefillin. is sufficient evidence? What’s the
resolution? So אמר רבה בר רב שילא, Amar Rabbah bar Rav Sheila,
כשרבו הניח לו תפילין. kesher rabo hiniyach lo tefillin. No, no, no.
You’re right. Those things are just that the master is present and
then it’s not sufficient evidence. But when the master is actively involved,
right, that would be different. So if the master actually said to
the גבאי, gabbai, I want you to give him an עליה aliyah
and here’s his name. That might be different than בפני רבו. Now
borrowing money and making him אפוטרופא, apitropas, right, that the master is
directly involved, but that’s maybe more a sort of like playing a
certain like type of a role in, you know, in business, might
be different than a social status that emerges from being involved in
like, you know, the ritual מצוות mitzvos of תפילין tefillin and בית
הכנסת Beis Hakneses and so on. That would more be something that
you would not, you know, that really would show evidence of this
person’s sort of, you know, participation in, you know, as a free
person at that certain type of societal level. Whereas the issue of
the business and the לוה loveh and the אפוטרופא apitropas less so.
So those,
but if he’s involved in those areas of the תפילין or whatever,
then that is evidence. Now תוספות Tosafos makes an interesting point, כשרבו
הניח לו תפילין. kesher rabo hiniyach lo tefillin. Because remember, the reason
before by the marry, the גמרא Gemara’s says because he wouldn't be
involved in having a slave do an איסור. issur. So תוספות Tosafos
by the תפילין says ולא משום דלא מעביד ליה איסורא דמברך עליהן
דאיכא ברכה לבטלה. velo mishum delo ma'avid lei issura demivareich aleihen de'ika
bracha levatalah. The problem is not that there's an איסור issur being
done that it’s a ברכה לבטלה bracha levatalah because slaves are exempt
from תפילין. דהא סוכה ולולב ושופר וכמה מצוות עשה שהנשים מברכות. deha
succah velulav veshofar vekama mitzvos asei shehanashim mivarchos. And it’s okay if
they’re exempt from a מצווה mitzvah to make a ברכה bracha like
women make a ברכה bracha which is the אשכנזי Ashkenazi approach. אלא
משום דאין עבדים רגילין בתפילין דלאו דשחרייה לא הוה מנח ליה. Ella
mishum de'ein avadim regilin betefillin dilav de'shachreih lo hava m'nach lei. Okay,
so it’s just because societally that’s not acceptable but not because there's
any הלכה halacha that's in the way, right? And by the way,
one can't help thinking about the issue that's going on here about
the sense about societal status associated with these types of ritual communal
מצוות mitzvos or not all communal but the תפילין and the עליות
aliyos and so on, you know, and how that sort of has
something to do with the contemporary issues that are going on around,
you know, about women's role in those types of areas as well.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
See I snuck that in. So now the גמרא Gemara continues the
following way. Okay,
אמר רבה בר רב שילא, Amar Rabbah bar Rav Sheila, כשרבו הניח
לו תפילין, kesher rabo hiniyach lo tefillin, we just said that. כי
אתא רב דימי אמר רבי יוחנן, Ki ata Rav Dimi amar Rabi
Yochanan, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came he said in the name
of רבי יוחנן, Rabi Yochanan, מי שאמר בשעת מיתתו Mi she'amar besha'as
misaso פלונית שפחתי אל ישתעבדו בה אחר מותי. ploni shifchasi al yishtabedu
bah achar mosi. So now we're done with those sort of events
that demonstrate that he's free and now we're getting back to ways
in which he becomes free. So somebody said as he was dying,
"This woman, my slave woman, my heirs should not enslave her after
I die." So כופין את היורשים וכותבין לה גט שחרור, kofin es
hayorshim vechosvin lah get shichrur, you force these heirs to write her
a גט שחרור get shichrur because he basically thinks that that's maybe
like a type of a לשון lashon that he's מפקיר mafkir her,
he no longer owns her, but she still needs a שטר. shtar?
That was that question before, you מפקיר mafkir your slave but needs
a שטר. shtar, He's dead, he can't write the שטר, shtar. the
heirs write the שטר. shtar. Now you might remember before there was
a question if the heirs don't own her, are they in a
position to write the שטר? Shtar. But anyway, that's what he's understanding.
She's not enslaved anymore but she needs a שטר, Shtar? the heirs
write the שטר. Shtar. כופין את היורשים וכותבין לה גט שחרור. kofin
es hayorshim vechosvin lah get shichrur. אמרו לפניו, Amru leifanav, they said
to him, רבי, והאמרינן רבי אמי ורבי אסי, veha'amrinan Rabi Ami veRabi
Assi, they said רבי אמי Rabi Ami and רבי אסי Rabi Assi
said to him, רבי, אי אתה מודה שבניה עבדים? iy atah modeh
shebaneha avadim? One minute, why should they free her? Still, I mean,
even if they're not allowed to work her, but she's still a
slave and they'll be able to work the kids that she has.
The kids that she'll have will be slaves. So why should they
be freeing her? Meaning they understood when they said, when the owner
said, "Don't work her, don't enslave her," he didn't say, "I'm renouncing
ownership over her." He's saying like, "Let her sit and watch TV,
you know, don't make her work for you. She's worked hard enough.
I'm not changing her status, she's still a slave, but she should
be entitled to, you know, to relax and not to be made
to work." Okay fine, so why should we free her? She's not,
well why are you keeping her a slave if she's not working?
Oh, keeping her a slave because any babies that she has, any
kids that she has, those will be slaves and those we'll be
able to enslave and to work. So why should we be freeing
her? Okay, so אי אתה מודה שבניה עבדים? iy atah modeh shebaneha
avadim? So therefore it was a question about whether that language אל
ישתעבדו al yishtabedu meant he was renouncing ownership or was he just
telling them not to work her. Okay, so כי אתא רב שמואל
בר יהודה אמר רבי יוחנן, Ki ata Rav Shmuel bar Yehudah amar
Rabi Yochanan, when רב שמואל בר יהודה Rav Shmuel bar Yehudah came
he said in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan's מי שאמר
בשעת מיתתו, Mi she'amar besha'as misaso, it's a different version, not אל
ישתעבדו, al yishtabedu, but here's what he said: פלונית שפחתי. ploni shifchasi.
she she she was a she she she did
very nice by me during my life, so יעשו לה קורת רוח.
ya’asu lah koras ruach. You should do to her what she what
you should do for her what she wants. So therefore, כופין את
היורשים לעשות לה קורת רוח. kofin es hayorshim la’asos lah koras ruach.
You force the heirs to free her. Not because he now renounced
ownership, but if you want to do to her whatever she do
for her whatever she wants, means free her. So he gave a
deathbed be- not bequest, a deathbed request, directive, right,
that this slave be freed. So it’s not like the other case.
The other case was a question: was he renouncing ownership or not
renouncing ownership? How to interpret it, what was it about, okay. Here
he’s clear, say do for her whatever she wants. So that is
a deathbed request that they that she be freed. Okay. So that’s
what the גמרא Gemara going to say. So מאי טעמא, mai ta’ama,
why do we force the heirs to do it? מצוה לקיים דברי
המת. mitzvah lekayem divrei hamess. It’s a מצוה mitzvah to do what
the what the person said if he said on his deathbed. Now
there’s a question under what parameters do we say that, right? What
constitutes דברי המת divrei hamess that we can’t that the heirs have
to do? And why do you force the heirs to do a
מצוה? mitzvah? That’s not like it’s legally binding. So that raises a
lot of interesting questions. But that’s different than דברי שכיב מרע. divrei
shchiv mera. דברי שכיב מרע divrei shchiv mera is a bequest, a
deathbed bequest which actually is binding automatically and the ownership transfers as
soon as the guy dies. Okay, and that actually has the force
of an act of transfer of property. Here he’s telling them, “Here’s
what I want you to do,” like דוד המלך, Dovid Hamelech, you
know, before he dies. He’s got to take care of this guy
and he’s got to take care of that guy. This is what
I want you to do. So that’s מצוה לקיים דברי המת. mitzvah
lekayem divrei hamess. And the question then becomes: when does בית דין
beis din force the heirs to carry that out? And here they
are. All right, אמר אמימר, amar Amimar, said
אמימר: Amimar: המפקיר עבדו אותו עבד אין לו תקנה. hamafkir avdo oso
eved ein lo takkana. We’re back to this. If you renounce ownership
of the slave, he’s stuck. Before we said we had three possibilities
what happens if you renounce ownership of the slave. שמואל says he
goes free automatically. The status follows the owner. The second opinion which
I forgot what but the major position that we’ve been dealing with
is the personal status issue is left. You still have to give
him a שטר שחרור shtar shichrur to change his personal status, but
you’re still in a position to do so because you still have
that master-slave relationship with him even though you no longer own him
as property. Third possibility is he needs a שטר שחרור shtar shichrur
to change his personal status, but nobody is left to do it.
Because since you no longer own him as property, that’s what you’re
saying David, you’re no longer his master. You can’t give him the
שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. So this slave is really stuck.
Not really stuck; at least he can work for himself and keep
his own labor, but he’s never going to become a free person
because nobody is alive, nobody exists anymore that’s in a position to
change his personal status. Okay. אותו עבד אין לו תקנה. oso eved
ein lo takkana. There’s no ways he can fix his his status
issue. So the גמרא Gemara says: מאי טעמא, mai ta’ama, why is
that? גופיה לא קני ליה איסורא הוא
דאיכא גביה ואיסורא לא מצי מקני ליה. gufei lo kani lei issura
hu d’ika gabei v’issura lo matzi makni lei. Wait a minute, yeah
okay. So גופיה, gufei, so because when he renounced ownership over the
slave, he didn’t give the slave- he
I’m sorry, let me say that, the owner no longer owns the
slave’s body as property. איסורא הוא דאיכא גביה, issura hu d’ika gabei,
all that’s left is- this is the word איסורא issura is the
גמרא Gemara language for what I’ve been calling personal status. Okay, the
איסור issur status-
the איסורים issurim that apply to a slave as opposed to a
free man or whatever, meaning the personal status is the issue that
remains by the slave. ואיסורא לא מצי מקני ליה. v’issura lo matzi
makni lei. And the owner is no longer in a position to
give him his personal status, to change his personal status because he
no longer owns him. Okay, so that’s the worst of all the
words. He needs it and he can’t get it.
You gave up the property and then but the status he’s stuck.
He’s stuck and he’s no longer in a position to change his
status. אמר ליה רב אשי לאמימר, amar lei Rav Ashi l’Amimar, so
רב אשי Rav Ashi said to אמימר: Amimar: והאמר עולא אמר רבי
יוחנן ורבי חייא בר אבין אמר רב, v’ha’amar Ulla amar Rabbi Yochanan
v’Rabbi Chiyya bar Avin amar Rav, but don’t we have these traditions:
אחד זה ואחד זה יצא לחירות וצריך גט שחרור? echad zeh v’echad
zeh yatza l’cheirus v’tzarich get shichrur? That’s what we taught two days
ago, okay, that when you renounce the ownership of it,
you- he’s no longer owned by you, but he still needs to
get שחרור shichrur and presumably can get שחרור shichrur from you, from
the master. You’re still in a position to give him גט שחרור.
get shichrur. He says, “No, you misunderstood their teaching.” אמר ליה: צריך
ואין לו תקנה. tzarich v’ein lo takkana. What they were saying was:
he needs a שטר שחרור shtar shichrur and he ain’t gonna get
it! So we thought that “needs a שטר שחרור” shtar shichrur means
you gotta finish it by giving a שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur, but
he’s saying: “What I’m saying they meant is he’s in a position
that he is not going to change his status until he gets
a שחרור shichrur and that isn’t ever going to happen.” Okay, so
that’s the worst of both worlds.
If the if the owner’s intent is so clear because he was...
no, the path to hell is paved with good intentions. I’m serious!
For ההלכה halacha you need to do the right act. I’m try-
I’ve been trying all this time to sell you my field. Okay?
It doesn’t matter, you didn’t do the legally binding act.
But why would it not have been the case that בית דין
beis din could then complete that?
Possibly, but what are you going to do? I mean we have
to have the rule of law. So every time somebody comes and
says, “You know...” how it was clear what I was trying to
do. Okay, in your case we'll say it'll be binding. What are
you going to do? I mean, I don't understand.
That happens in court all the time.
Oh, I don't know, but not in הלכה. Okay? We're not going
to go case by case and say you can't live in a
world in which you don't know the rules of the game, that
anybody could just petition the court and get them to say, "Well,
okay, in your case it'll work." That's anyway, so we're not going
to do that. So the גמרא says like this.
Where were we? Okay. אמרת ליה לא קנה. Asarta leh lo kana.
איכא דאמרי Ika d'amri some say אמר אמימר, Amar Ameimar, המפקיר עבדו
ומת אותו עבד אין לו תקנה, Ha-mafkir avdo u-meis oso eved ein
lo takana, that אמימר Ameimar said he's stuck. I'm sorry, no. Not
that you're מפקיר mafkir and you're alive. You're מפקיר mafkir and you're
alive, that's what we've been assuming until now, you can still fix
it. You still have a master relationship to him even though you
don't own him and you can still give him a שטר שחרור.
shtar shichrur. That's what we've been assuming. Okay, but the one case
where he really is stuck is the guy is מפקיר mafkir him
and dies. Then nobody has that relationship with his slave.
The heirs don't because they didn't inherit him as property. The only
person who had that relationship is now dead. Okay. המפקיר עבדו ומת
אותו עבד אין לו תקנה. Ha-mafkir avdo u-meis oso eved ein lo
takana. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? גופיה לא קני ליה. Gufey lo kani
leh. At the when he freed the when he renounced ownership he
did not give the slave his
I'm sorry, I think I misread that before also. גופיה לא קני
ליה. Gufey lo kani leh. Right, here's what it means. He no
longer owns the slave's body. He no longer owns the slave as
property. איסורא הוא דאיכא גביה. Issura hu d'ika gabei. The only thing
that remained was the status issue. Now if he was alive, he
was still in the position to change the status. But איסורא לבני
לא מוריש, Issura l'vnei lo moris, but he doesn't transfer that status
to the children. Right? So if the children don't own the slave
as property, they never become the slave's master. And the one person
who was the slave's master and who could have retained that title
and status after he no longer owned him, that guy is dead.
So now the slave is stuck. Okay. אמר ליה רב אשי לאמימר,
Amar leh Rav Ashi l'Ameimar, said רב אשי Rav Ashi to אמימר,
Ameimar, דהא כי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי יוחנן, D'ha ki asa
Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan, but what about the story of רב
דימי אמר רבי יוחנן? Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan? That was the
story earlier when the guy said, "Oh, my slave woman, don't be
משעבדא meshabbda her," and then he died. Okay, so what did we
think? So we thought,
remember that case? We just had it a few minutes ago. We
thought that meant that he was being מפקיר mafkir her and then
it ended by saying we forced the heirs to redeem her. So
that's a case of המפקיר עבדו ומת mafkir avdo u-meis where that
the הלכה was we would force the heirs to redeem her. So
that's against you. So he says back, no. גבי דדימי טעות היא.
Gabei d'Dimi taus hi. One minute, but that was, don't you remember
that that whole פסק psak was a mistake? Because the pushback that
they gave, right? They said, "Well, what about the babies?" and he
actually said he didn't really renounce ownership, he really just said, "Don't
make her work." So the גמרא says, fine. אמר ליה מאי טעותא?
Amar leh mai tausai? So why was it a mistake? דלא אמר
בלשון שחרור. D'lo amar b'lashon shichrur. It the principle wasn't at stake,
what was wasn't the issue. The question was what did the guy
say? The pushback was he didn't say, "I'm renouncing ownership," he just
said, "Don't make her work." Right? Remember that whole exchange? And therefore
they said, "Okay, fine, she's a slave until she'll produce babies." But
nobody was challenging the principle. If he had said explicitly, "I'm renouncing
ownership," everybody would have been happy. He would have died and the
heirs could have freed her. So that tells you that the heirs
can free a slave even after the owner has renounced ownership. הא
אמר בלשון שחרור, Ha amar b'lashon shichrur, had he said the right
language, had he said, "I'm renouncing ownership," הכא נמי, hacha nami nobody
would have debated the principle that the guy renounced ownership, he died,
and the heirs could free. So you see that there is that
position out there that the heirs can just do the status issue.
אמר ליה אנא כרב שמואל בר יהודה סבירא לי. Amar leh ana
k'Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda sevira li. I hold like רב שמואל בר
יהודה Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda who says that the heirs are who
had a different version of רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's teaching. That version
of רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's teaching was אל ישתעבדו בה. al yishtabdu
bah. But the other version of רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan teaching was
קורת רוח עשתה לי. koras ruach asta li. Right? Remember that we
had those two cases back-to-back? So the קורת רוח עשתה לי, koras
ruach asta li, when he was commanding them to free her, it
was מצוה לקיים דברי המת. mitzvah l'kayem divrei ha-meis. So that says
nothing about this case. So your evidence was a version of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. about "don't make her work," I had a different
version of that whole פסק psak of that teaching of רבי יוחנן.
Okay, so now we have a debate about whether המפקיר עבדו ומת,
mafkir avdo u-meis, whether the heirs are enough in a position to
do the status issue.
In the facts of the case and the consideration, he's מפקיר mafkir
and then before he then continues and says משוחרר, meshuchrar, he drops
dead.
Well, not says, before he gives the שטר. Shtar Right. ההוא דיסקרא
דעבדי, Hahu diskara d'avdei, there was a certain a city of slaves,
maybe a district, I don't know, that's probably a Latin word, you
can tell me what Steinsaltz says. Greek. From the middle Greek, yeah.
דיסקרא diskara meaning an inherited plot of land.
Oh, plot of land.
Okay, he translates it as a city.
Okay, fine. A certain city, a certain region of slaves דאיזדבן לעובדי
כוכבים, d'izdaban l'akum, that they were all sold to non-Jews. כלה מר
ובא בתר בתריה. kala mar u-vasar basrei. Now the second owners, the
non-Jews, they all died, who bought these slaves.
You're not allowed and that's exactly true. And if you sell your
slave to a non-Jew, you have an obligation to free your slave.
And that's exactly what's going to happen here. So now the non-Jews,
the owners are those who... those owners aren't around, the masters now
have a religious obligation, a legal obligation to free the slaves. They're
not free automatically. They have to give the... they have to give
them a שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. But there's going to be a
little bit of a problem. אתו קמיה דרבינא atu kamei d'Ravina they
came, the slaves came to רבינא. Ravina. אמר להו amar lehu he
said to them, זילו הדור אבני מר בר רב אשי קמאי. ziloo
hadiru ab'nei mar bar Rav Ashi kamai. Now the slaves, the original
masters had all already died. But who was alive were the children
of those original masters. Go to those children, ויכתבו לכו גיטא דחירותא
v'yichtevu lacho gita d'cheruta and they'll write a שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur.
So you understand though, this is essentially a case about מפקיר עבדו
ומת. mafkir avdo u'mes. As soon as they sold their slaves to
the non-Jews, they renounced property ownership. But they still had an obligation
to write a שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. And then they died. And
now he's saying go to the sons, they'll write it. So he's
basically saying מפקיר עבדו ומת mafkir avdo u'mes you can be כותב
kosev שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. אמרו ליה רבנן לרבינא amru leh rabanan
l'Ravina so the Rabbis said to רבינא, Ravina, והאמר אמימר המפקיר עבדו
ומת אותו העבד אין לו תקנה v'ha'amar Ameimar hamafkir avdo u'mes oto
ha'eved ein lo takana that after you... that you have no... that
you're stuck in that case. אמר להו amar lehu he said to
them, אנא כרב דימי סבירא לי ana k'Rav Dimi sevira li I
hold like the רב דימי Rav Dimi story where he said like
אל ישתעבדו בה al yishtab'du bah and that shows that... and that
the heirs would... would free the slave. So אמרו ליה amru leh
they said to him, דרב דימי טעותא היא d'Rav Dimi ta'uta hi
what do you mean? That case was a mistake because they said
that he wasn't really freeing her, he was just saying don't make
her work. So אמרו ליה amru leh what... מאי טעותא mai ta'uta
why was it a mistake? דלא אמר בלשון שחרור. d'lo amar b'lashon
shichrur. It wasn't... the principle wasn't at stake, they were just saying
he didn't say he was release... he was renouncing ownership. He just
said he... he just said don't make her work. הא אמר בלשון
שחרור ha amar b'lashon shichrur had he actually said that he was
renouncing ownership, הכא נמי
nobody is debating the principle that he would have renounced ownership, he
would have died and the heirs would have freed her. So we
actually פוסק pasken מפקיר עבדו ומת mafkir avdo u'mes that we actually
say that the heirs can be
משחרר. mishachrer. והלכתא כרבינא v'hilchata k'Ravina and we rule like רבינא. Ravina.
Okay. So therefore we rule מפקיר עבדו ומת mafkir avdo u'mes the
slave is not stuck, the heirs are in a position to free
the slave. That they actually also get that status, you know, the
ability to affect the status. Okay. Let's see if we can turn
the page before the end of the דף. daf. We'll remain just
a half a דף daf behind. ההוא עבדא דבי תרי hahu avda
d'bei trei there was a slave owned by two people. קם חד
מינייהו ושחרריה לפלגיה kam chad minaihu v'shachreye l'palgei one of them got
up and freed... released his half. Gave him a שטר שחרור. shtar
shichrur. So this is, of course, the... how you get the scenario
of חצי עבד וחצי בן חורין. chatzi eved v'chatzi ben chorin. All
right. אמר אידך amar idach the other said, השתא שמיע לי ברבנן
ומפסדי לי מינאי. hashtah shmiah li b'rabanan u'mafsedi li minai. So the
other one said, wait a minute, because we're about to learn in
a משנה Mishna one of the תיקון עולםs tikkun olam is that
when a slave is in that position, he's in the worst of
both worlds. He can't marry a free woman because he's half slave,
he can't marry a slave woman because he's half free. So he's
never going to be able to have kids, he's never going to
be able to get married. So the Rabbis said what you have
to do is you have to force the master, the remaining master,
to free the slave. Now the remaining master knew this and he
didn't want to give up his half ownership of the slave. So
guess what he did? So... אזל אקניה לבנו קטן azal akneye l'vno
katan so he went and he transferred ownership to his minor son.
So therefore they won't be able to force my minor son, right?
They're not going to force a minor. So... now it's protected, at
least as long as the son remains a minor. Okay.
Can a minor own property?
Yes, they can. Certainly. And you can also transfer through a third
party. There are times... there's some times that they can actually take
possession themselves, but I can also transfer it through a third party
who can take possession for them, okay, on their behalf. So now
the minor owns him, but the Rabbis... won't force him to do
anything. So
שלח רב יוסף בריה דרבא לקמיה דרב פפה. shlach Rav Yosef brei
d'Rava l'kamei d'Rav Papa. So he sent this case, right, רב יוסף
Rav Yosef sent this case to רב פפה. Rav Papa. What are
we going to do about this case? And actually it's not just
one case. If we allow this loophole, everybody else is going to
figure out this loophole too. So שלח ליה shlach leh he sent
back to him, כאשר עשה כן יעשה לו גמולו ישיב לו
בראשו. ka'asher asah ken ye'aseh lo gemulo yashiv lo b'rosho. Okay. You've
got to do back to him what he did to... what he
did. He's trying to trick the situ... to trick, you know, the
system. We're not going to let him trick the system. We're... we're
going to trick him back. So what are we going to do?
So אנן קימלן בינוקא דמקרבא דעתיה לגבי
זוזי. anan kimlan b'yanuka d'mikarva datei l'gabei zuzei. We know kids, like,
if they see money, right, they'll... they can be easily seduced by
like I'll buy you a nice toy or whatever. Okay. Anyway. So
מוקמינן ליה אפוטרופוס mokminan leh apotropos
we assign a... a guardian. Okay. Now we'll discuss in a minute
what the guardian does. ומקשקשי ליה זוזי u'makashkashi leh zuzei and we...
jingle some money in front of the kid.
Okay. Or the slave jingles some money in front of the kid.
וכתב ליה גיטא דחירותא אשמיה v'chosev leh gita d'cheruta ashmei
and then he writes a שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur. Now who is
the one who is writing the שטר שחרור? shtar shichrur? So what?
And what's the role of the אפוטרופוס? apotropos? Right? So רש"י Rashi
says, one minute... one minute... to protect... right... to protect the child.
Right.
Right. Hold on, just want to just remind myself of the debate
of רש"י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot, one minute.
Right. So רש"י Rashi says that the... that the child writes a
שטר שחרור shtar shichrur and that a child actually if he's of
a... of enough age can be involved in these types of transactions.
תוספות Tosafot disagree. תוספות Tosafot says that a minor is not in
a position if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says
פירוש הקונטרס, Perush HaKuntres, second line of
תוספות, Tosafot, דמפרש אשמעתא דקטן שאימת הקטן כלום לטיבא ובשחרורין
כמו קטן. demafersh ashmeita dekatan she'eimas hakatan kelum lativa uvashichurin kemo katan.
Sorry, start from the beginning. לא נהירו לבינו שמואל פירוש הקונטרס. Lo
nehiru lebeinu Shmuel perush hakuntres. רבינו שמואל Rabbenu Shmuel doesn't agree with
רש"י's Rashi read of this גמרא because
רש"י Rashi explains דמפרש אשמעתא דקטן demafersh ashmeita dekatan that the גט
get. is written, the minor is the one who gives the
גט. get שאימת הקטן כלום לטיבא ובשחרורין כמו קטן שקנה יבמתו מן
התורה דאינו נותן גט עד שיגדיל. she'eimas hakatan kelum lativa uvashichurin kemo
katan shekana yevamto min hatorah de'eino nosei get ad sheyagdil. If the
גט get, is personal status issue, even if a minor has the
ability to engage in some degrees of transaction, he does not you
need to be an adult to affect somebody's personal status, right? And
therefore he says the minor cannot write the שטר. Shtar, Who writes
the שטר? Shtar. The אפיטרופוס Apitropus writes the שטר. Shtar. So תוספות
Tosafot says the אפיטרופוס Apitropus is assigned to be the one to
write the שטר Shtar once he's a guardian of the minor, okay,
but you could say it's not in the best interest of the
minor, but you know what? He's going to get paid when you
write the שטר שחרור Shtar Shichrur to free the other half of
the slave, the slave owes the half of the money.
And therefore, but we don't want the minor yelling and screaming and
saying this is against my will, this isn't in my best interest,
so in order to calm down the minor that he doesn't complain,
we're going to jingle some money, we'll give him a toy, we'll
give him whatever, and he won't complain, and the אפיטרופוס Apitropus is
the one who's empowered to write it. And then תוספות Tosafot has
the whole question: is that a power the אפיטרופוס Apitropus has, is
that an עיקר הדין, Ikar HaDin, or is that only a type
of a הפקר בית דין הפקר Hefker Beis Din Hefker that we
had to do in this case? But can the אפיטרופוס Apitropus of
a קטן, katan, is he empowered as a principle of law to
free a slave? רש"י Rashi says, but either way תוספות Tosafot says
he's the אפיטרופוס Apitropus is writing it and the קטן katan is
the one who's being consulted, being tricked by the toy. רש"י Rashi
actually says that no, you get the קטן katan to write it,
a קטן's katan empowered to write a גט, or is able to
write a גט שחרור, get shichrur, and then what does the אפיטרופוס
Apitropus do? The אפיטרופוס Apitropus makes sure that you assign a good
value to the slave, since the slave is going to have to
pay back his value, the אפיטרופוס Apitropus is assigned to make sure
that we agree on a fair price. But so what it ends
with is a fascinating debate of רש"י and תוספות Tosafot about whether
a minor can write a שטר שחרור, Shtar Shichrur, which, you know,
gets to that whole status versus property issue. Yes.
Is the רבינו שמואל Rabbenu Shmuel mentioned here in תוספות Tosafot רש"י's
grandson?
Yeah, I believe that's the רשב"ם. Rashbam. Okay. So if people are
willing to give me a few more minutes, let's just try to
get caught up. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. עשיתי פלוני עבדי בן חורין,
Asiti ploni avdi ben chorin, עשוי בן חורין, asui ben chorin, הריהו
בן חורין, hareihu ben chorin, הרי הוא בן חורין. harei hu ben
chorin.
So if somebody says, and we're going to say in a minute
writes in the שטר שחרור, Shtar Shichrur, I have made, interesting, even
though it's the language of the past, we're going to interpret to
mean through this I have made my slave free, or he's becoming
free, behold he is free, all of those are legitimate languages in
a שטר שחרור, Shtar Shichrur, even though you would have thought that
the language of past wouldn't work. אעשנו בן חורין, Asenu ben chorin,
I will make him free. רבי אומר קנה, Rebbi omer kana, that
means I will make him free through this שטר, Shtar okay, וחכמים
אומרים לא קנה. vachachamim omrim lo kana. No, that's just a promise,
you're not actually freeing him now. And אמר רבי יוחנן וכולן בשטר.
v'amar Rabbi Yochanan vekullan bishtar. All of those are the language in
a שטר. Shtar, What you say with words doesn't matter, it's the
language of the שטר. Shtar. And let's continue also read the next
case, it'll go very fast. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. נתתי שדה פלוני
לפלוני. Nasati sadeh ploni leploni.
So the same way a שטר Shtar to free a slave, you
have a שטר to transfer property. So if you write in the
שטר, I have granted, again even in the past, I have granted
this field to this person, it's a gift. נתונה לפלוני, nesunah leploni,
it is given to so-and-so, הרי היא שלו, harei hi shelo, or
behold this field is his, in all those cases הרי היא שלו,
harei hi shelo, that works. אתננה לפלוני, Etenenah leploni, I will give
it to so-and-so. רבי אומר קנה, Rebbi omer kana, that works, you
mean I'll give it through this שטר. וחכמים אומרים לא קנה, vachachamim
omrim lo kana, it doesn't work. ואמר רבי יוחנן וכולן בשטר, v'amar
Rabbi Yochanan vekullan bishtar, all of this is the language in the
document. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. עשיתי פלוני עבדי בן חורין, Asiti ploni
avdi ben chorin, והוא אומר לא עשאני. vehu omer lo asani. So
you say, I made him free, and he says, you didn't make
me free. חיישינן שמא זיכה לו על ידי אחר. Chashenan shema zika
lo al yedei acher. So we don't trust the slave because he
could have freed him without the slave being around. He could have
given a שטר שחרור Shtar Shichrur to somebody else on behalf of
the slave, right? Because that's considered to be the slave's benefit, the
slave doesn't have to assign a שליח. shaliach. So the slave might
think he didn't free him but he maybe really did. Now let's
say he says, let's say the claim is כתבתי ונתתי לו, kasavti
venasati lo, I gave him a שטר שחרור Shtar Shichrur directly to
the slave, והוא אומר כתב לי ולא נתן לי, vehu omer kasav
li velo nasan li, לא כתב לי ולא נתן לי, lo kasav
li velo nasan li, no he didn't. So הודאת בעל דין כמאה
עדים דמי. hodas ba'al din kemei'ah edim dami. We trust the admission
of the person who is the litigant, his admission counts as 100
witnesses. Now whose admission?
I'm the owner, I'm admitting that it's not my property, so I'm
hurting myself. You're the slave, you're admitting that you're not free, you're
hurting yourself. Who's the הודאת בעל דין? hoda'as ba'al din? You understand
the question here? They're both hurting their own interests in a certain
way, but the גמרא means is the slave is the one who
is believed. Why? The way תוספות Tosafot explains it is because was
I you can understand a scenario where I gave it to my
slave, and my slave was not really agreeing to the process, was
not really desiring to accept it and was not really agreeing. So
it looked like I was freeing him but he wasn't, and therefore
we'll believe the slave. But there's no scenario where I wrote the
שטר and gave it and I didn't really mean what I was
doing. Okay? So therefore, because that's like a believable scenario, we actually
choose we actually believe the slave. הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים דמי
Hoda'as Ba'al Din k'Me'ah Eidim Dami and he's not free. האומר נתתי
שדה פלוני לפלוני, Ha'omer Nasasi Sadeh Ploni l'Ploni, הוא אומר לא נתת
לי, hu omer lo nasas li, similar case: I gave it and
he says you didn't. חיישינן שמא זיכה לו על ידי אחר. Chayshinan
shema zika lo al yedei acher. We assume he gave it to
a third party. Okay. כתבתי ונתתי לו Kasavti v'nasati lo והוא אומר
לא כתב ולא נתן לי, v'hu omer lo kasav v'lo nasan li,
let's say you say, I gave it directly to him, and he
says, no, you didn't. הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים דמי. Hoda'as Ba'al
Din k'Me'ah Eidim Dami. The guy who is refusing the present, like
the slave was refusing himself as a present, you believe him and
the gift is not binding. Now, מי אוכל פירות? Mi Ochel Peiros?
Who eats the fruit? Now, what do you mean who eats the
fruit? We just said we don't believe him. I mean, you know,
we believe that it wasn't a gift. So we'll see in a
minute a case where we're not exactly sure what happened. In a
case where we're not sure what happened, who benefits from the field
until it gets or you know until it gets resolved? So רב
חסדא אמר: Rav Chisda amar: נותן אוכל פירות. Nosen ochel peiros. If
we don't believe that it happened, the gifter is the one who
it's now his field, so he benefits from it. ורבה אמר: V'Rabbah
amar: משלשין את הפירות. Meshalshein es hapeiros. No, you have a third
party take care of them and you know you put it in
escrow until the whole thing gets resolved. Now, why when are we
putting it in escrow? We said that we believe the receiver, he
didn't receive it, it all belongs to the original owner. So the
גמרא says: ולא פליגי. V'lo pligi. הא באבא הא בברא. Ha b'abba
ha b'bra. If the father says, I never accepted it, then we
100% believe the father and it 100% is owned by the original
owner and the original owner gets the fruit benefit. But if the
son says, you never gave it to my father, well we're not
so sure. Maybe the son doesn't really know. So in that
case we have held in escrow the benefits of the field until
somehow they work something out to resolve it. Okay, there we go.